<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://deep.mpi-inf.mpg.de/DAC/files/style/deep_process_style.css"?>
<process>
    <name>TEPIC</name>
	<version>1</version>
	<author>
		<name>Florian Schmidt</name>
		<email>fschmidt@mmci.uni-saarland.de</email>
	</author>
    <description>
	The TEPIC (Transcription Factor Annotation using an Epigenetic Prior) process can be used to obtain scores describing the affinity of Transcription Factors (TFs) to a set of genes considering a  predfined area around their 5' transcription start site (TSS).
	We utilise TRAP (Transcription Factor Affinity Prediction, cf. http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/23/2/134.long) to obtain the aformentioned scores. By default, peak scores
	are combined to gene scores in a 50kb window using exponential decay (Ouyang et al, 2009). In addition, TEPIC offers reweighting TF scores within peaks using the signal of the open chromatin assay within a peak. 
	Furthermore, TEPIC computes purely statistical features inferred only from the provided epigenetic data, such as peak count, aggregated peak length and aggregated peak signal. 
	The process takes a region file in bed format as input (e.g. DNase1-seq peaks, or TF-footprints), a reference genome, a gene annotation file in gtf format, and a set of position specific energy matrices (PSEMS, e.g. from the Jaspar database). 
	Note that regions, which are shorter than any PWM, can not be considered
	In addition, the user has to specify the SampleID and the number of cores that should be used for running TRAP.
 	To run the process use the script TEPIC.sh. 
	The command line including all possible options is: <command_line><![CDATA[./TEPIC.sh  -g {genome_reference} -b {region_file} -o {prefix} -p {pwms} -c {cores} -d {signal_file} -a {genome_annotation} -w {window} -n {column} -e {decay} -f{gene_filter_file} -l{length_normalisation} -u{peak_features} -x{original_scaling} -m{motif_length} -y{genebody} -z{gzip} -k{background_regions} -r{2bit_reference_genome} -v{p-value} -i{minutes} -j{Chr_prefix}]]></command_line>

	The basic functionality can be achieved using the following command line: <command_line><![CDATA[./TEPIC.sh  -g {genome_reference} -b {region_file} -o {prefix} -p {pwms} -c {cores} -a {genome_annotation} ]]></command_line>

	</description>

	<inputs>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>region_file</identifier>
			<format>bed</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>TF prediction will be carried out in all valid regions specified in this file.</comment>
		</filetype>

		<filetype>
			<identifier>signal_file</identifier>
			<format>wig</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>Signal of the open chromatin assay. The calculated TF affinities are scaled according to this signal. 
				This should not be used if NOMe data is utilised. In that case, provide the -n parameter. That will cause TEPIC to extract the average signal within a peak out of the specified column in the region_file.</comment>
		</filetype>

		<filetype>
			<identifier>background_regions</identifier>
			<format>bed</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>Manually derived regions to be used for assessment of the background TF affinities.</comment>
		</filetype>

	</inputs>
	<references>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>genome_reference</identifier>
			<format>fa</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>The reference genome of the analysed organism.</comment>
		</filetype>

		<filetype>
			<identifier>genome_annotation</identifier>
			<format>gtf</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>A genome annotation file (gtf) used to extract the position of the TSSs.</comment>
		</filetype>

		<filetype>
			<identifier>2bit_reference_genome</identifier>
			<format>2bit</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>A file containing the reference genome in 2bit format</comment>
		</filetype>

		<filetype>
			<identifier>pwms</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>A file containing PSEMs</comment>
		</filetype>
	</references>

	<outputs>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>affinity_file_peak_view</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>This file contains the so called affinity scores computed by TRAP for all regions in the region_file such that at least one PWM is sufficiently large to cover the region. </comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>affinity_file_gene_view_filtered</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>Using the genome_annotation, we compute an additive affinity score, using exponential decay, for all genes by overlapping all regions of the affinity_file_peak_view  with a window of size 50000bp centered at the TSS of each gene. Genes located outside the window are removed in this file. The -e option allows to deactivate the exponential decay.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>signal_scaling_factors</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>File containing the average per base signal of the open chromatin assay for all peaks contained in the file affinity_file_peak_view.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>scaled_affinity_peak_view</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>Contains the scaled affinities per peak and TF.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>scaled_affinity_gene_view_filtered</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>Scaled version of the file affinity_file_gene_view_filtered.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>affinity_gene_view_peak_features_signal</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>TF-gene scores with additional features for peak count and aggregated peak length and signal.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>affinity_gene_view_peak_features</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>TF-gene scores with additional features for peak count and aggregated peak length.</comment>
		</filetype>
		<filetype>
			<identifier>sparse_affinity_gene_view</identifier>
			<format>txt</format>
			<quantity>single</quantity>
			<comment>File listing only TF-gene relationships above the provided significance threshold.</comment>
		</filetype>


	</outputs>

	<software>
		<tool>
			<name>bedtools getfasta</name>
			<version>2.25.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[bedtools getfasta -fi {genome_reference} -bed regions_fitered -fo temp_file]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>Creates a fasta file containing the sequences for all regions listed in the file regions_fitered.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>convertInvalidCharacterstoN.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python convertInvalidCharacterstoN.py temp_file temp_file2]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>As TRAP accepts only A, C, G , T, and N we replace all characters unequal to those by N.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>TRAPmulti</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[./TRAPmulti ${pwms} ${prefix}-FilteredSequences.fa $cores]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>This script uses a parallelized C++ implementation of TRAP to compute transcription factor binding affinities.
			It requires . The tool can be build by running the script compile_TRAP_install_R_packages.sh.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>computeDNaseCoverage.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python computeDNaseCoverage.py {signal_file}_sorted > {signal_scaling_factors}]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>Computes the per base coverage in the NFRs, using a sorted version of the user specified bedgraph file.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>scaleAffinity.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python scaleAffinity.py {signal_scaling_factors} {affinity_file_peak_view} > {scaled_Affinity_peak_view}]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>Multiplies the peak centric affinites with their corresponding scaling factors.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>filterInvalidRegions.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python filterInvalidRegions {affinity_file_peak_view}_temp {affinity_file_peak_view}]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>This script removes regions in case that we could not make any TF binding predictions. This happens if the regions in the region file are shorter than any PWM. This is also carried out for the file scaled_affinity_file_peak_view_temp</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>annotateTSS.py</name>
			<version>3.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python annotateTSS.py {genome_annotation} {affinity_file_peak_view} --geneViewAffinity {affinity_file_gene_view} --windows {window} --decay {decay} --signalScale {scaled_affinity_file_peak_view}]]></command_line>
			<loop></loop>
			<comment>This python script computes gene specific TF scores using the files affinity_file_peak_view and if available scaled_affinity_file_peak_view generated in the TRAP.R3script. Gene_view files provide affinity scores for all TF and all genes in the genome_annotation. The window size determines the size of the window around each TSS. Decay indicates if the aggregation uses exponential decay. If the affinity values should be scaled with the signal strength of the open chromatin assay, the scaled_affinity_file_peak_view file has to be provided.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>filterGeneView.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python filterGeneView.py {*_gene_view}]]></command_line>
          	<loop></loop>
			<comment>This python script removes all genes from the *_gene_view file that are not located in the window used during the annotation.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>findBackground.py</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[python findBackground.py -i ${filteredRegions}_sorted.bed -g ${randomGenome} -o ${prefix}_Random_Regions.bed -w ${cores} --time-out ${minutes}]]></command_line>
          	<loop></loop>
			<comment>This python script computes background regions to assess the significance of TF affinities.</comment>
		</tool>

		<tool>
			<name>IdentifyCut-Offs.R</name>
			<version>1.0</version>
			<command_line><![CDATA[Rscript IdentifyCut-Offs.R  ${affinity}_Random ${affinity}_temp ${prefix}_Filtered_Affinities_temp.txt ${pvalue}]]></command_line>
          	<loop></loop>
			<comment>Calculates a threshold to binarise TF affinities with respect to the provided p-Value and the background affinities.</comment>
		</tool>


	</software>
</process> 
